你好,学生
hello students
我是Yan，今天我们要讨论二进制文件
I'm Yan and today we're going to talk about binary files
这是基础系列的一部分
this is an entry in our Fundamental Series
学习这门课
to approach this class
你应该已经掌握了该知识
you should really already have this knowledge
如果你在这里存在一些空白
in case there are gaps in your knowledge
希望该视频能填补上
this should hopefully fill them in
但如果跟不上这个视频
but if you are really lost throughout this whole video
请先看懂，再继续后面的课程
please go back and make sure you know this material before taking this course
好了，我们开始吧
all right let's roll
我们先说一下/bin/cat
we're gonna be talking about /bin/cat
/bin/cat是Linux及类似系统中的程序，用于
/bin/cat is again the Linux utility for, and related systems
怎么了
what
什么情况
what's going on
/bin/cat简单好用
bin cat is nice and simple
它就是向你输出东西
it just echo stuff out at you
如果我们
if we
实际上，我们不用/bin/cat
we'll actually instead of bin cat
用我们自己写的cat代替一下
be using our replacement little cat that we wrote
这样方便搞事情
so you can mess around with it in clever ways
代替品先输出个字符串
our replacement prints some silly string
再输出给定的文件
and then writes out the file that it was given to write out
也可以给它其它文件
you can also do other files
或标准输入
and standard in
很酷的小工具
very cool utility
总之，/bin/cat是一个程序
anyways that /bin/cat is a program
是从C代码编译成的所谓的ELF文件
that is compiled from C into what is called an ELF file
什么是ELF文件呢
so what is an ELF file
ELF为可执行可链接格式
an ELF file stands for Executable and Linkable Format
规定了程序是如何加载到内存并执行的
defines a program as it will be loaded and executed in memory
它规定了程序在磁盘上的存储格式，以及启动方式
so it defines it at rest on disk and enables its execution
ELF存储了一大堆程序信息
ELF stores a whole bunch of data about a program
例如，为哪种架构编译的
for example what architecture is compiled for
这是一个64位x86架构的ELF
so this is a 64 bit ELF for x86
当然还有用于识别自身是ELF文件的数据等等
and of course identifies itself as an ELF and so forth
在其他操作系统上
on other operating systems
还有其他格式的可执行文件
there are other formats for executable
在Linux上是ELF
so on Linux it's an ELF
freeBSD也是
freeBSD also
在Windows上
on Windows
可执行文件是所谓的PE文件
executables are what are known as PE files
可移植可执行文件
Portable Executables
在MacOS上是Mach-O
on MacOS it's Mach-O
等等
and so on
ELF以及类似的文件格式
so ELF and related formats there
或多或少都很相似
they're all more or less similar
它们都能让编译器或类似的东西
they all allow a compiler or something
创建并定义一个程序
to create and define a program
我们继续
let's move on
ELF都包含什么
what does an ELF contain
ELF包含很多东西
an ELF contains a bunch of stuff
主要可以分成ELF的两种视图
but mostly contains two views into itself
一是它如何加载以及执行（内存视图）
one of them is how it should be loaded and executed
二则更多是语义上的内部有哪些数据（文件视图）
and another one is more semantic information about what the data inside it is
我们先谈谈第一个
let's talk about the first one first
这些是程序头
these are called program headers
它们定义了所谓的segment
and they define what are called segments
segment是ELF执行时加载到内存的部分
segments is the parts of an ELF file that are loaded into the memory of a computer when that file is executed
主要有两种类型
and there are two main types
我们看一下
let's take a look
可以用readelf程序查看程序头
so you can look at headers with the readelf utility
它能解析ELF
you get it parse out an ELF
告诉你所有你想知道的
and tell you everything you wanted to know about it
我们看一下cat
let's look at cat
我们的cat很简单
our cat here is pretty simple
先滑到最上面
scroll all the way up first
首先
first things first
所有ELF都以7f 45 4c 46开头
all ELF start with the bytes in hexadecimal 7f 45 4c 46
你应该能认出，在ASCII编码中这是ELF
you should be able to recognize that in ASCII coding this spells E L F
所以ELF文件开头为7F ELF
so ELF starts with 7f E L F
实际上这就是识别ELF文件的方法
this is actually how file recognizes that it's an ELF
然后还在ELF头中定义了很多东西
then it defines a bunch of stuff in the header format
如我们说过的，它是64位的
that it's 64 bit as we discussed etc
要说的一点是它的Entry Point（入口地址）
one thing I'll point out is it defines its entry point
ELF加载到内存后，程序会在0x10e0处开始执行
execution will begin after the ELF is loaded into memory  at 10e0
我会在该系列后面的部分讨论加载与执行
I'll talk about the loading and execution in the later part of the fundamental series
我们现在看看程序头
but let's move on to the program headers
程序头定义了将加载到内存中的segment
so program headers define segments that will be loaded in memory
这里有四个
there are four of them here
第一个在文件的最开头
this first segment starts at the very beginning of the file
这是偏移量，然后是文件大小
so it's offset then file size
这表示从文件里的这个地址开始加载多少数据
then this is from inside the file how much data will be loaded from which location
然后这个表示
and then here it is
要占多少内存，以及存在哪里
how much will be actually stored in memory and where
这个虚拟地址
the virtual address
我会在讲加载的视频中详细讨论
and I'll talk more about this in the loading video
如今计算机软件里的虚拟地址是经过随机化处理的
but the virtual address nowadays for modern software on modern computer is randomized in memory
使程序更安全一点
to make the program a little more secure
更能抵御某些类型的攻击
and more resilient to certain classes of attack
这是到那个随机化基址的偏移量
and this is an offset from that location
在文件的开头
so at the beginning of the file
有0x700字节
there are hexadecimal 700 bytes
这是加载在最开头的0x700字节
this is 700 base 16 that are loaded to the beginning
不管该文件最终加载到哪，之后的头0x700字section
first 700 bytes of memory wherever this file is chosen to be located
然后在偏移值0x1000处
then there is at an offset of hexadecimal 1000
即10进制的4KB处
which is actually 4 kilobytes in decimal
4KB是一个内存页的大小
also 4 kilobytes in that is the size of one page
我们将在后面的模块中讨论内存页和虚拟内存等
we'll talk about pages and virtual memory and so forth in a later module
加载0x335字节数据，后面以此类推
we load 335 in hexadecimal bytes and so on for the rest of these
要提一点的是，这些数据的权限是不同的
one thing I'll mention is the permissions of this data are different
第一个被加载的数据是作为可读数据加载的
so the first data that's loaded is just loaded in as readable data
这0x335B是加载为可读可执行的
this hex 335 is loaded as readable and executable
还有一个是可读的
and then there's one that's loaded as readable
和一个可读可写的
and one that's loaded as readable and writeable
之后会发现这很重要
this is important later you will see that
这些不同的segment包含不同类型的数据
these different segments contain different types of data
有一点很重要
it's important to mention that
这些程序头定义的segment
these segments defined by program headers
是信息源
are the source of information
是基于此来加载ELF文件的
the ground truth for loading this ELF file
你可以构建一个只有程序头的ELF文件
you can build an ELF file that has nothing but program headers
它将是一个非常有问题的ELF文件
it'll be a very broken ELF file
但一会要讲的
but everything else I discuss from now on
它会崩溃，但能执行
it'll be broken but it will run
但一会要讲的
everything else I'll discuss from now on
多多少少是可选的
is more or less you know optional
它们的存在是为了便于执行
fluff to make our lives easier
还有一件事
one other thing
这个INTERP程序头挺有意思的
this interp header is a very interesting one
能在readelf输出的这里看到它
you can see it right here in the output of readelf
INTERP表示
and INTERP says okay
它不是用于加载的
it's not a load directive
所以它不会向内存中加载任何东西
so it doesn't load anything into memory
不会导致内存占用增长
or causing anything grow this memory
它表示在文件的0x318偏移处
but it says that at hex 318 in the file
有0x1c字节的数据
there is some data 1c in size
稍等
one second
我回来了
I'm back
对不起，我得让我的猫离开房间，它被困住了
sorry I had to let my cat out of the room he was stuck
有0x1c字节的数据
there's some data hex 1c in size
指定用于或说助于将该ELF加载到内存的库
that specifies the library that is going to load or help load our file into memory
讲可执行文件的加载时，我会详细讨论这个问题
I'll talk about this at length when I talk about loading of these executables
但是现在
but for now
我先在KaitaiStruct程序中向你展示
let me show you in a program called Kaitai Struct
大概是什么样的
what this looks like
这是KaitaiStruct
so this is Kaitai Struct
这是一个基于web的IDE
it's a web based IDE for looking at
或说基于web的程序，用于查看文件的结构
or web based program for looking at structured files
比如可执行文件的，或者png、zip等
such as executables but also things like PNGs zip files etc
上传我们的cat文件
so let's upload our cat file
打开它
open it up
它会以一个项打开
it's opening it as a key
哦，这里有个ELF
oh there's an ELF here's an ELF okay
将其解析为ELF
so parsed it as an ELF
我们可以深入到
we can drill into
这里是魔数（固定特征值）
so again here is the magic numbers
你能在这个侧边看到16进制视图
you can see a hex view on the side here
这是7f，然后是ELF
here is 7f and then you see ELF
太棒了
awesome
我们深入了解一下这个interp
let's dig in to this interpreter
我们看到这个interp的偏移值是0x318
we see this interpreter has an offset of 318
如果你滑倒0x318这里
and if you scroll in 318 here
这正是加载器的路径
we see this is exactly the path of the interpreter of the loader
它负责加载此文件及其依赖项
that will be responsible for loading this file and its dependencies
酷
cool
我们把目光从segment与程序头转向section头
let's move on from segments and program headers to section headers
我刚意识到
I just realized that
这是之前的ppt，哦，没问题
it was the previous slide the previous slide was good okay
等等，我把相机隐藏一下
hold on I'm gonna hide my camera
这样你们就能清楚地看到幻灯片
so you can see the slide properly
好的，我马上回来，别担心
boom okay I'll be right back don't worry
好的，section头
so section headers
section头代表ELF文件的另一种视角
section headers represent a different view into an ELF file
这个视图有更多的语义信息
it's a view that has a lot more semantic information
在加载过程中不太重要
and is less important for the actual loading process
如我所说
like I said
我见过根本没有section头的elf文件
I've seen ELFs that don't have section headers at all
一般来说，用起来肯定不是很有趣
generally speaking they are not very fun to work with
我不确定你是否可以在没有section头的情况下动态加载
I'm not actually sure that  you could have it dynamically loaded without section headers
但这是有可能的
but it might be possible
不管怎样
anyways
section定义了segment中实际包含的内容
sections define what the segments actually have inside them
不是从数据角度
not from a data perspective
而是从含义角度
but from a meaning perspective
但含义一般对于
but that meaning is only really important for the most part
逆向工具、调试工具、理解ELF以及ELF管理工具是很重要的
to reversing tools debugging tools and introspection of the ELF and tools to manage ELFs
我们过一遍，我回来了
so let's walk through I'm back
我们过一下一些重要的
let's walk through the important ones that
一些重要的section
some important sections
有.text段
there's the text section
它里面是可执行代码
it has the executable code
不是英文之类的文本
it's not text as an English text
它是二进制的
it is the binary
是编译后的源码
the compiled source code
或者说是要执行的程序汇编代码
or assembled assembly code of your program that will be executed
.plt和.got都是用于
plt and got are used to
解析和转接程序中使用的库调用（重定位）
resolve and dispatched library calls that you use in your program
比如你的C程序调用了printf
for example if your C program calls printf
plt中会为printf创建一段数据
there will be a stub created for printf in plt
它是一段代码
which is a section of code
我们马上会看看
we'll take a look in a second
修改它，再在后续模块深入研究
edit it at a high level and we'll look more in depth at this in future module
里面有一段代码
there's a stub there
第一次调用printf时
the first time you call printf
会执行这段代码
that stub will run
开始解析libc库中
initiate the process of resolving where in the library in libc
在你加载的版本的libc中的printf的地址
in the specific version of libc you have loaded and so forth printf is
它会找到printf地址，然后存在got中
then it will find that address store it in the got
got用于保存找到的地址
which will be used to catch that location
使库调用处理的更快
to make this process faster
所以plt和got一起用于解析和转接库调用
together plt and got are sections that are used to resolve and dispatch library calls
还有运行时plt不关心这个section的名字叫got
again at runtime the plt doesn't care about the name got of a section
直接硬编码了一个偏移值
it just has an offset hard coded in
所以如果你正常加载，即定义了程序头的话
so if you load them properly which is defined the segment headers
就能正常工作
they'll work
数据
data
这里有三种类型的数据section
there are three types of data sections that are defined
一个是.data
one is .data
它里面放着有初始值的全局可写数据
it defines global writable data that has an initial value in the file
当把东西载入内存时，它已经有了一个初始值
so when you load something into memory it already has an initial value
就比如说，你C代码中硬编码的
this is if your C code has some sort of hard coded array in it for example
全局可写的数组
that you can then later edit a global array
.rodata类似，但用于只读数据
.rodata is similar but for read only data
比如，我们写的cat
so this is for example in our version of cat
我的shell怎么了
what is going on with my shell
好的，等一下，我要
okay hold on I'm gonna wow
我可能弄崩了啥
I broke something
这就是cat
so here's cat
能看到cat先输出了HAHA!
you saw that cat prints ha ha
这很好
that's this good
它在输出任何东西前，先输出HAHA!
right now it prints ha ha before it prints anything else
再执行cat的功能，输出给定文件
does its cat thing
这个HAHA!就是存储在rodata中的只读数据
this ha ha is read only data that will be stored in the rodata section
我们马上会用到它
we will mess with that in a second
然后还有用于存储全局未初始化数据的bss
and then there's the bss which is used for storing uninitialized readable data that's global
比如说，在c代码中定义的一个没有初始值的全局数组
so an array defined in your C code that doesn't have an initial value
还有如果在C代码中定义一个巨大的没初值的数组
the idea is if you define a giant array in your C code doesn't have initial value
那么该数组就没有理由占用ELF文件中的任何空间
there's no reason for that array to take up any space in the ELF file
这只是在浪费文件大小
it's just a waste of file size
所以与其从文件中加载bss数据到内存
so instead that is rather than being loaded from the file
不如分配内存时全置为零
it's just allocated with all zeros
我已经特别提到过，section头不是
I specifically mentioned that already section headers are not
我去掉我的头像，这样就能看了文字了
let me disappear so you can read this
section头不是ELF的必要部分
section headers are not a necessary part of the ELF
实际上你遇到的ELF基本都有它们
I mean realistically almost every ELF you'll ever interact with will have them
但它们不是必须存在的
but they are not strictly necessary
ELF可以没有section头
an ELF can exist without section headers
它们只是元数据
they are mostly just metadata all right
符号和符号解析
symbols and symbol resolution
我先关一下摄像，方便看这个链接
again let me disappear for a second so you can see that link
elf中有符号，本质上就是名字
ELFs have symbols which means names essentially
它们使用的依赖于其它库的名字
that they use names that rely to constructs of other libraries
比如其它库导出的函数和变量
such as functions and variables exported by those libraries
它们用这个名字来找到合适版本的库
that they use to find libraries of correct versions
解析函数，等等
resolve functions and then and so forth
这是一个非常复杂的过程
this is a very convoluted process
涉及多个表
involving multiple tables
其它表的表内偏移值
offsets into other tables
字符串表等
tables of strings etc
我强烈推荐这个博客系列
I highly recommend this blog post series
马上还有其它该系列的链接
I'll have another link to there in a second
它详细深入地描述了
but it really describes in very in depth detail
它的工作原理
how all of this works
如果你感兴趣的话可以看一看
you can take a look if you're very interested
但在本课程中，不需要如此深入
but you won't need to interact with ELF files in so much depth in this class
例如，这个图表摘自本系列博客文章
this diagram for example is taken from this series of blog posts
如何与ELF交互
how do you interact with your ELF
有很多很多的工具
well there's a ton tons and tons of tools
你可以用它们来与你的ELF交互
that you can use to interact with your ELF
我们已经见过的KaitaiStruct
we already saw Kaitai Struct
我在里面点来点去，看了ELF的各个部分
saw me clicking around and looking at parts of the ELF
用gcc制作elf文件
you make the ELF with GCC
你还看到了我用的readelf
you saw me use readelf
我快速展示一下nm的用法
let me show you real quick nm being used
nm从ELF文件中读取符号的工具
so this nm is a utility that reads symbols from the ELF file
比如-D
so -D for example is
用于查看所有动态导入的符号
how to resolve to look at all of the dynamic imports
这些是这个程序运行时使用到的函数
so these are functions that the program will use at runtime
可以看到open put读取和写入
you can see the open puts read and write
我将在以后的视频中讨论__libc_start_main
__libc_start_main is something I'll talk about in the future video
它用于初始化或者说开始执行
it's used to initialize or to begin execution
以后再谈它
talk about it later
当然你可以查看更多的符号
you can of course look at more symbols
这些是所有的符号
these are all the symbols
包括该程序定义的符号
including symbols that the binary define
比如我们可以找到main的地址
so for example we can probably find the address of main
这是main的地址
yeah so here's the address of main
就在11c9
at this 11c9
在入口地址后面不远处
shortly after the entry point
我们之后会讨论为什么
and we'll discuss why at a later time
patchelf是一个很酷的工具
patchelf is a cool utility
它能用奇怪的方式修改ELF
that can mess with your ELF in weird ways
你可以用它注入与所需加载的不同的库
you can inject different libraries that are going to be needed to be loaded
更改我前面提到的INTERP加载器等
change around that interpreter that I mentioned and so on
objcopy也很酷
objcopy is pretty cool
objcopy可以让你导出、修改、导入section
objcopy can allow you to export mess with and then import sections
我们导出所有cat的section
so let's dump out this section of cat
rodata，如果还记的，它表示只读数据
the rodata if you recall that is the read only data
在这个rodata中有HAHA!
and that rodata has this ha ha in it
所以如果你cat一下刚刚导出的
so if you look at what we just dumped out
它先输出HAHA!，接着rodata中的HAHA!
it prints out the ha ha then it's the HaHa
还是用hexdump看一下吧
let's take a look at the hexdump
这是rodata中的内容
this is what was in the rodata section
这是其它的只读数据
because there was some other read only data
然后是我们字符串的ASCII码
and then there was the string in ASCII of course
HAHA!
ha ha exclamation point
有趣的是
interestingly
如果我们看一下
if we look at
我们用vim打开，然后改成hello
we grab vim and we change this to something like hello
这次不用--dump-section了
and then instead of dump section
我们用--update-section
we do update section
读入该文件，写到cat的rodata中
to read in that file and write it into that section in cat
我们这就修改了这个程序
we just modified this file
现在执行cat，它将先输出Hello
if we do cat now it'll print hello
虽然源码中写的是HAHA!
even though the original source code had ha ha
对于这段代码
just as for this code
如果只是这样的一个简单修改，不需要漏洞利用
you don't need to exploit if it's a simple edit like that
可以直接改二进制文件本身
I could just modify the binary itself
vi -b启用了二进制编辑模式
vi -b enables binary mode
且vim在编辑时，会禁用一些能弄乱二进制文件的东西
and vim disable some things that might mess up the binary during editing
但这非常非常简单
but this is super super simple
比如，我可以查看hello在哪里
like I can go and look at where hello is
然后改成BYE!!!
and say bye
现在
and now
它会输出BYE!!!
it say bye
当然，在section中改更友好
but of course it's a little friendlier to do it on the section
一次改一个section
one section at a time
我们后面也会用objcopy来帮助编写shellcode之类的
we'll also use objcopy later for help when we're writing shellcode and stuff in later modules
最后一件事
the final thing
这里的一堆符号
there's a bunch of symbols here
它们有助于调试等等
they help with debugging and so forth
但它们会占用空间
but they take up space
可能会提供你不想让别人知道的关于程序的信息
and might give people more information than you want them get at your binary
你可以用strip，去除它们
you can use strip to strip them away to remove them
执行strip cat
strip cat
没了
it's gone
好的
okay
strip有很多不同的参数
strip has a ton of different options
你可以用strip去除更多东西
that you can strip out more and more things
比如去除整个section之类的
remove whole sections and so forth
我们不深入研究
we're not going to go into them
就这样
and this is it
我再次强烈推荐这一系列深入研究ELF格式的文章
again I highly recommend this series of posts digging into the ELF format
我希望本期视频是有用的
and I hope that this was useful
希望现在你对ELF了如指掌了
that you now know ELFs like the back of your hand
这对整个课程都有帮助
and that it'll help throughout the course
下次见
see you in the future